Bryant Bannister Papers, 1934-2009 (bulk 1950-1990)
University of Arizona Library Special Collections
Bryant Bannister Papers1934-2009(bulk 1950-1990)
MS 508
University of Arizona Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccol/
Bannister, Bryant
6 linear feet
This collection includes the correspondence and administrative files of Dr. Bryant Bannister during his tenure at the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research, University of Arizona, and additional personal files of Dr. Bannister's including, research interests and colleague collaboration, writings and professional papers, thesis and dissertation, conference or business trips, and lecture class notes and syllabi from teaching while at the University of Arizona
None.
Biographical Note
Dr. Bryant Bannister is emeritus director (1964-1982) of the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research and emeritus professor (1959-1989) of dendrochronology and archaeology at the University of Arizona. He was born in Phoenix, Arizona on Dec. 2, 1926 and received his B.A. from Yale University in 1948, his M.A. in 1953 and his Ph. D. in 1960 both from the University of Arizona. He studied under A. E. Douglass, the first director of the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research, serving as his assistant through most of the 1950’s. He met Emil Walter Haury, a noted Southwest archaeologist and director (1938-1964) of the Arizona State Museum as an undergraduate at the Point of Pines Field School in the summer 1948 and continued his graduate studies under his direction. He married Betty Stanaway on August 22, 1951 and they have two children, Nancy Beth and Frances Kimball.
Dr. Bannister is the fourth director (1964-1981) of the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research, founded in 1937 by Douglass, astronomer Edwin Francis Carpenter (1898-1963), and Emil W. Haury. During his tenure as director, he was instrumental in supervising the updating of the entire Southwestern tree-ring chronology. He also served as associate/assistant and acting dean of the UA College of Earth Sciences between 1971-1982.
Dr. Bannister's subject specialties were archaeological tree-ring dating in the US and the Southwest and dendrochronology worldwide. He began his teaching career in dendrochronology, the science of dating annual growth layers in woody plants, in 1959, and was an assistant professor from 1960-1964, associate professor in 1964, and full professor from 1965 until his retirement in 1992.
His publications include his M.A. thesis, Tree-Ring Analysis As Applied to the Dating of Kin Kletso Ruin, Chaco Canyon, New Mexico, (1953) and his Ph.D. dissertation, Tree-Ring Dating of Archaeological Sites in the Chaco Canyon Region, New Mexico (1959). He co-authored the tree-ring dating publications issued by the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research that covered Arizona, New Mexico and parts of Utah, including:
Tree-Ring Dates from Arizona E: Chinle, de Chelly, Red Rock Area (1966)
Tree-Ring Dates from Arizona N-Q, Verde, Show Low, St. Johns Area (1966)
Tree-Ring Dates from Arizona K: Puerco-Wide Ruin-Ganado Area (1966)
Tree-Ring Dates from Arizona J: Hopi Mesas Area (1967)
Tree-Ring Dates from Arizona C-D, Eastern Grand Canyon, Tsegi Canyon, Kayenta Area (1968)
Tree-Ring Dates from Utah, S-W, Southern Utah Area (1969)
Tree-Ring Dates from New Mexico A, G-H: Shiprock-Zuni-Mt. Taylor Area (1970)
Tree-Ring Dates from New Mexico M-N, S, Z, Southwestern New Mexico Area (1970)
Tree-Ring Dates from Arizona U-W: Gila-Salt Rivers Area (1971)
He also wrote chapters in books, articles for the Laboratory Bulletin of Tree-Ring Research, the Tree-Ring Bulletin, the American Journal of Archaeology, the American Antiquity, other journals and proceedings, and numerous reviews and editorials.
Dr. Bannister is a fellow in the American Anthropological Association and the American Association for the Advancement of Science, a member of the Society of American Archaeology, the Tree-Ring Society and its editor of their Bulletin from 1958-1969, a member of the Arizona Academy of Science, Phi Kappa Phi, Pi Mu Epsilon, the Society of Sigma Xi (Arizona chapter president 1968-1969), and Sigma Alpha Epsilon.
Tree-Ring Bulletin/Tree-Ring Research
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series.
Series I: Biographical,1954-2002
Series II: Correspondence, A-Z1950-2007
Series III: Laboratory of Tree-ring Research, 1934-2009
Subseries I: Administrative Files, 1934-2009
Subseries II: University of Arizona, 1966-1987
Subseries III: Grants, 1960-1974
Series IV: Research
Series V: Writingsy
Series VI: Teaching
Series VII: Travels
Series VIII: Audiovisual Materials
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of Dr. Bryant Bannister from 1934 to 2009, bulk from 1950-1990, when he served as director of the University of Arizona's Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research and professor at the UA. It includes administrative files and correspondence, grants submitted, subject material on his research interests, sabbaticals, correspondence and documentation of work with other colleagues, lecture notes and syllabi from his teaching profession in dendrochronology and archaeology, original manuscripts of his publications, including his dissertation and thesis, travels and personal biographical material.
Arizona State Museum; University of Arizona. Laboratory of Tree Ring Laboratory; Central Arizona Project (U.S.); Bannister, Bryant; Blanchette, R. A. (Robert A.); Damon, Paul E., 1921-; Danson, Edward Bridge, 1916-2000 -- Correspondence; Douglass, A. E. (Andrew Ellicott), 1867-1962; Eddy, John A.; Fagette, Paul, 1947-; Ferguson, Charles Wesley; Fred C. Henson Company; Gell, Jonathan -- Correspondence; Giddings, J. Louis (James Louis), 1909-1964-- Correspondence; Gladwin, Harold S. (Harold Sterling), 1883-1983 –- Correspondence; Haury, A. N. (Agnese Nelms); Haury, Emil W. (Emil Walter), 1904-1992; Haynes, C. Vance (Caleb Vance),1928-; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976 -- Correspondence; Kuniholm, Peter Ian -- Correspondence; Libby, Willard F.; Lindsay, Alexander J. -- Correspondencepersname; McGraw, Donald J.; McGregor, John C. (John Charles), 1905-1992 -- Correspondence; Markgraf, Vera; Odishaw, Hugh; Osborne, Douglas -- Correspondence; Pilcher, Jon R. -- Correspondence; Renfrew, Colin, 1937-; Schulman, Edward M.; Smiley, Terah L. (Terah Leroy), 1914-; Vivian, Gordon -- Correspondence; Wasley, William W. (William Warwick), 1919-1970; Webb, George Ernest -- Correspondence; Coelostat; Dendrochronology; Dendroclimatology; Radiocarbon dating; Radiometers; Rocky Mountain bristlecone pine; Tree-rings; Casas Grandes Site (Mexico); Chaco Canyon (N.M.)
- Biographical1954-2002, Series I
  This series contains biographical information about Dr. Bannister including his honoraria and societies
  - Biographical1954-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Societies and Honoraria (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, A-Z1950-2007, Series II
  - Correspondence, A1958-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, B1958-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, C,1951-2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, D1958-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Danson, Edward B.1959-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, E1955-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, F1957-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, G1958-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Gell, Jonathan1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Giddings, J. L.1958-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Gladwin, Harold S.1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, H1950-2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, I-J1958-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Judd, Neil M.1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, K1962-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Kuniholm, Peter I.1972-2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, L1960-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Lindsay, Alexander J. Jr.1957-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, M1956-1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, McGregor, John C.1958-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, N-O1955-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Osborne, Douglas1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, P-Q1955-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Park, Won-Kyn1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Pilcher, Jon R.1937-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, R1952-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, S1952-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Schweigruber, Fritz, H.1974-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Sleeper, H. Presoctt, Jr.1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, T1955-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, U-V1958-2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, University of Pennsylvania1958-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, University of Pennsylvania1963-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Vivian, Gordan1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Vivian, Gordan1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, W1955-1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Webb, George E.1983-1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, X-Z1961-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research1934-2009, Series III
  The series contains the business files received from Dr. Bannister related to the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research
  - Administrative Files 1934-2009, Subseries I
    This subseries is arranged chronological then alphabetically by topic
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1934-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files2000-2009 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Agnese Haury Fund1993-2008 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Annual Reports1954-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Arizona State Museum1984-1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files1961-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Fred C.Henson Company1966-1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Inquiries1951-1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Laboratory Equipment Development1956 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Laboratory Equipment Development1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Laboratory Equipment Development1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Laboratory Equipment Development1966-1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Nitrate Film1936-1952 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Stadium Construction1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Staff Meetings1966-1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Administrative Files: Staff Meetings1980-1992 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - University of Arizona1966-1987, Subseries II
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: University of Arizona: Centennial1985 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: University of Arizona: College of Earth Science1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: University of Arizona: Dept. of Geochronology1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: University of Arizona: Geoscience Dept.1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: University of Arizona: School of Renewable Resources1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: University of Arizona: Sunset Review, Lab of Organic Geochemistry1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Grants 1960-1974, Subseries III
    This subseries is arranged chronologically
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: National Science Foundation Institutionals1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Dendrochronological Study of the Casas Grandes Site, Chihuahua, Mexico 1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Completion of the First Turkish Tree-Ring Study1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: A Synthesis of Southwestern Dendrochronology1963 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Dendroclimatic Series in Western North America(NSF)1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Dendrochronology of Southwestern United States (NSF GS-247) 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Dendrochronology of Southwestern United States (NSF GS-908) 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Dendrochronology of Southwestern United States (NSF) 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research: Grants: Tree-Ring Investigations in the Italian Peninsula1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Research, Series IV
  Series IV contains folders on Dr. Bannister’s research interests including, collaborative work with colleagues, noted under the colleague, and specific subjects.
  - A. E. Douglass Films (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Archaeological Survey of Sonora, Mexico Expedition (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Bailey, Dana K.1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Bailey, Dana K.1960-1977 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Blanchette, Robert A. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Bristlecone Pine (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Central Arizona Project (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Cycloscope (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Czechoslovakia Tree-Rings (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Damon, Paul E. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Douglass, A. E. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Early Peoples, Prehistory and Tree-rings (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Eddy, John A. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Fagette, Paul H., Jr. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Ferguson, Charles Wesley (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Haury, Emil W. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Haynes, C. Vance (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - History of Dendrochronology (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Japan, Oldest Tree (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Japanese Cypress section1963-1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lehman, Juan Charles (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Libby, Willard F. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Markgraf, Vera (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - McGraw, Donald J. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Odishaw, Hugh (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Radiocarbon Dating (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Radiometer and Siderostat (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Renfrew, Colin (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Schulman, Edward (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Smiley, Terah (Ted) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Tree-rings (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Tree-Rings and Environment Newsletter (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Tree-rings, Metal Tungsten, Cancer (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Tree-ring Research Worldwide (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Tripitaka Koreana (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - University Indian Ruins Site (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - University of Arizona Eclipse Expedition of 1923 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Wasley, William Warwick (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Writings, Series V
  Series V contains Bannister's writings, published and non-published, including his master’s thesis and doctoral dissertation.
  - Correspondence 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis 1987 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Dendrochronology (unpublished) (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Dendrochronology chapter in Science in Archaeology1963 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Dendrochronology and Radiocarbon Dating: The Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research Connection by Steven Leavitt and Bryant Bannister2009 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Dendrochronology in the Near East: Current Research and Future Potentialities (unpublished) (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Reviews (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Tree-Ring Analysis As Applied to the Dating of Kin Kletso Ruin, Chaco Canyon, New Mexico Master's Thesis Correspondence1951-1954 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Tree-Ring Analysis As Applied to the Dating of Kin Kletso Ruin, Chaco Canyon, New Mexico Master's Thesis Manuscript1953 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Tree-Ring Dating of Archaeological Sites in the Chaco Canyon Region, New Mexico Pd.D. Dissertation Manuscript1959(1 of 3) (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Tree-Ring Dating of Archaeological Sites in the Chaco Canyon Region, New Mexico Pd.D. Dissertation Manuscript1959(2 of 3) (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Tree-Ring Dating of Archaeological Sites in the Chaco Canyon Region, New Mexico Pd.D. Dissertation Manuscript1959(3 of 3) (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Tree-Ring Dating of Archaeological Sites in the Chaco Canyon Region, New Mexico Technical Series, 6.21965 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Teaching, Series VI
  This series contains Dr. Bannister's lecture notes and syllabi for courses taught at the University of Arizona.
  - Courses Anthropology 160a, 160b, Geochronology 295, Climatology1951-1963 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Course Geochronology - Dendrochronology 1761955 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Course Geochronology - Dendrochronology 2851955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Courses Anthropology – Dendrochronology 3011956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Courses Anthropology 295, 311a1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lectures, Addresses, Presentations1960-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Lectures, Addresses, Presentations198-2003 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Travel, Series VII
  Series VII contains information on Bannister's professional and sabbatical travels and conference presentations.
  - 12th Annual Symposium Paleoecology and Ethnobotany of the Southwest1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 35th Congress Mexico1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 36th International Congress of Americanists1964 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Aegean Dendrochronology Project1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Conferences and Trips, Various Locations1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Conferences and Trips, Various Locations1961-2008 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Egypt and Lebanon1965 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - International C14 and H3 Dating Conference1965 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - International Conference on the Application of Science to Medieval Archaeology1967 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - International Radiocarbon Dating Conference1972 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Royal Society and British Academy Symposium, London England 1969 and Oxford University 1970 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Sabbatical1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Sabbatical1982(1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Sabbatical1982(2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Science Partnerships in Action1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - University of Arizona Delegation to China1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - University of Wisconsin, Madison1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Audiovisual Materials, Series VIII
  - Audio tape 1. Ferguson, UCLC lecture at the International Conference on the Application of Science to Medieval ArchaeologyOctober 27, 1967. Recorded on DeJUR magnetic tape for dictating and transcribing machines (DeJUR- Amsco Corporation, Long Island City 1, New York), Audio tape 2. "Used tape Bannister." Recorded on Scotch 3M 290-1/4-600-LL. Contents and date unknown (Box 8, Folder 6)